Inventory of the Norman Drachler papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Norman Drachler papers
1945-1985
85020
Hoover Institution Archives
194 manuscript boxes (77.6 linear feet)
Minutes, reports, studies, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed matter relating to public education, primarily in Detroit.
Drachler, Norman.
Access
Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Norman Drachler was a teacher, educational integration advocate, superintendent for the Detroit school system, and the founder of an urban educational institution.
Born May 20, 1912 in Kaminetz-Podolsk, in what is now Ukraine, Drachler and his family immigrated to Detroit in 1929. He received a bachelor's degree (1937) and master's degree (1939) in education from Wayne State University, and he eventually went on to receive a doctorate in education from the University of Michigan (1951).
Drachler began his teaching career in the Detroit school system in 1937 and became superintendent in 1966. During his tenure as superintendent, Drachler worked on integrating both the administration and student body. He increased the percentage of African-American teachers by 40% and advocated to prohibit schools from purchasing textbooks that published negative images of minorities.
After resigning from the Detroit school system in 1971, Drachler founded the Institute for Educational Leadership, first at George Washington University and then in Palo Alto. The foundation provided a unique training program for administration and staff working in urban school districts. Drachler retired in Arizona and passed away in Phoenix in May 2000.
Scope and Content of Collection
Minutes, reports, studies, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed matter relating to public education, primarily in Detroit.
Education--Michigan--Detroit.
- Detroit
  - Proceedings of the Detroit Board of Education, 1945-1959 (Boxes 1-6)
  - Proceedings of the Detroit Board of Education, 1960-1974
  - Citizens' Committees on Schools, 1957-1968 (Boxes 6-9)
  - Decentralization, other cities, and national views (Boxes 10-15)
  - Detroit and Michigan materials: Education, demographic data, and Michigan Constitutional Convention of 1962-1963 (Boxes 15-18)
  - Educational finance - Detroit and other cities (Boxes 18-28)
  - Educational finance - national literature
  - Educational finance - federal and state reports, and various pamphlets
  - Federal programs and compensatory education (Boxes 28-37)
  - Compensatory education - national
  - Federal government in education - hearings, acts, data on American education
  - Public school publications to staff and community (Boxes 37-40)
    Scope and Contents note
    Also includes curriculum and plant evaluations.
  - Newspaper clippings from newspapers in Detroit and other cities: schools in the news, 1961-1980 (Boxes 40-55)
  - Newspaper clippings from newspapers in Detroit and other cities on one or several topics
- Detroit and other cities
  - Curriculum, 1958-1967 (Boxes 55-57)
  - Textbooks, 1967
  - Juvenile delinquency and youth (includes dropouts from school), 1965-1968
  - Large cities, employment, 1962-1963
  - School finance and federal aid, 1958-1969 (Boxes 57-59)
  - Integration - civil rights, 1956-1969 (Boxes 60-63)
  - Large cities, 1961-1964 (Boxes 63-65)
  - Segregation, 1964
  - Delinquency, 1963-1964
  - Poverty program and welfare, 1965
- National materials (Boxes 66-67)
  - Culturally deprived
  - Large cities
  - Leadership
- Education materials: Reports from other cities: Seattle, Los Angeles, Boston, St. Louis, San Francisco, and others (Boxes 68-71)
- Urban America - education: Reports, articles, books (Boxes 71-73)
- Detroit
  - Computer printouts: Selected data for decentralization study, selected data on federal and state programs, and selected data (Boxes 74-75)
    Includes information on each school by region, indicating expenditure per child in each school and other relevant materials, such as achievement on national tests, etc.
  - Educational evaluation (Boxes 76-78)
  - High schools (Boxes 77-81)
  - School reports and riot of 1967 (Boxes 81-84)
  - The courts and education (Boxes 85-86)
  - Collective bargaining - Detroit and nation (Boxes 87-88)
  - Student unrest - Detroit and nation (Boxes 89-91)
  - Educational reports (Boxes 91-98)
- National materials
  - Administration - general (Boxes 99-101)
  - American education - policies, politics, and critics (Boxes 102-104)
  - Assessment of education (Boxes 105-107)
  - The courts and education (Boxes 107-109)
  - Disadvantaged in education - nation (Boxes 109-111)
  - Education - other cities (Boxes 112-115)
  - Ethnics and education - nation (Boxes 115-117)
  - Hispanic and Indian education - nation (Boxes 118-119)
  - School integration - general (Boxes 119-123)
  - Segregation - education - nation (Boxes 123-125)
  - Teacher education - nation (Boxes 126-128)
  - United States Civil Rights Commission - reports (Boxes 128-132)
  - Urban America - education: Reports, articles, books (Boxes 132-134)
  - Urban Task Force - integration - nation
  - International education (Boxes 135-140)
  - Publications: National Education Association and American Association of School Administrators (Box 140)
  - Reports from other cities: Seattle, Los Angeles, Boston, St. Louis, San Francisco, and others
  - Culturally deprived, large cities, leadership
  - Disadvantaged in education - nation
  - Education - other cities
  - Educational issues during the 60s and 70s (Boxes 141-143)
  - Equal educational opportunities - Senator Mondale, chairman - reports and related articles (Boxes 143-145)
  - Ethnics and education - nation
  - Federal government and education (Boxes 145-148)
  - Hispanic and Indian education - nation
  - National education data
    - Student unrest - women in education (Boxes 149-151)
    - I.Q. - re-organization (Boxes 152-154)
    - Ability grouping - instruction (Boxes 155-158)
    - Research - youth (Boxes 159-161)
  - Coleman Report and related materials (Boxes 162-163)
  - Higher education and miscellaneous (Boxes 163-166)
  - Publications: National Education Association and American Association of School Administrators
  - Reports from other cities: Seattle, Los Angeles, Boston, St. Louis, San Francisco, and others
  - School integration - general
  - Segregation, education - nation
  - Teacher education - nation
  - United States Civil Rights Commission - reports
  - Urban America - education: Reports, articles, books
- Detroit
  - Collective bargaining - Detroit and nation
  - Student unrest - Detroit and nation
  - Educational reports
  - Newspaper clippings by subject areas (Boxes 166-172)
    Subjects include Detroit, curriculum, cities, general education, tests and I.Q., integration, courts and schools, and others.
  - Reports on Detroit public schools: population data, housings, etc. (Boxes 172-174)
  - Overlays for overhead projector: Demographic materials indicating relationships between educational achievement and health, housing, income, and race (Boxes 174-176)
  - Public school files: Negotiations, research, etc. (Boxes 177-179)
  - Reports and some related statements and articles by the superintendent (Boxes 179-181)
  - Detroit school election data on requests for additional funds and miscellaneous (Boxes 182-184)
- National materials
  - Administration - general
  - American education - policies, politics, and critics
  - Assessment of education
  - The courts and education (Boxes 185-186)
  - Urban Task Force - integration - nation
  - Urban Task Force and related materials (Boxes 187-189)
  - White House Conference for Children and Youth (Boxes 189-191)
- International education
- Detroit educational evaluation (Boxes 191-193)
- Minutes (Box 194)